export const ECONOMICSA2020 = [

{
id: "question1",
question:  "1. Which of the following is central to the definition of Economics?",
A: "Scarcity",
B: "Wants",
C: "Resources",
D: "Capital",
answer: "A. Scarcity",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question2",
question:  "2. When the production possibility curve shifts outwards, the economy experiences",
A: "over-production.",
B: "growth.",
C: "inefficient use of resources.",
D: "under-production.",
answer: "B. growth.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question3",
question:  "3. Land as a factor of production is made useful through the",
A: "application of fertilizer.",
B: "acts of nature.",
C: "application of human effort.",
D: "use of machines.",
answer: "C. application of human effort.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question4",
question:  "4. In a free market economy, resources are allocated through the",
A: "price mechanism.",
B: "government department.",
C: "trade union.",
D: "state planning committee.",
answer: "A. price mechanism.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question5",
question:  "5. The diagram above depicts a",
A: "simple bar chart.",
B: "complex bar chart.",
C: "multiple bar chart.",
D: "component bar chart.",
answer: "D. component bar chart.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question6",
question:  "6. Which of the following caused the change in the demand from D1D1 to D2D2?",
A: "Fall in the income of consumers",
B: "Fall in the supply of commodity X",
C: "Rise in the price of a complement",
D: "Rise in the price of a substitute",
answer: "D. Rise in the price of a substitute",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question7",
question:  "7. The curves D0D0 and S0S0 are the initial demand and supply curves respectively. What happens when government provides subsidy to producers?",
A: "The demand curve will shift from D0D0 to D1D1",
B: "The supply curve will shift from S0S0 to S1S1",
C: "The supply curve will shift from S0S0 to S2S2",
D: "The supply curve will shift from S1S1 to S0S0",
answer: "C. The supply curve will shift from S0S0 to S2S2",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question8",
question:  "8. In the graph above. YZ represents",
A: "excess demand.",
B: "equilibrium price.",
C: "equilibrium quantity.",
D: "excess supply",
answer: "D. excess supply.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question9",
question:  "9. Goods are described as inferior if their demand",
A: "decreases as price falls.",
B: "decreases as income increases,",
C: "increases as income rises.",
D: "increases as price increases.",
answer: "B. decreases as income increases,",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question10",
question:  "10. A consumer is in equilibrium when",
A: "his market supply is equal to his market demand.",
B: "he has consumed all he wants.",
C: "the market is also in equilibrium.",
D: "he maximizes his satisfaction from spending his income.",
answer: "D. he maximizes his satisfaction from spending his income.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question11",
question:  "11. Goods that are abundant in supply usually have low",
A: "total utility.",
B: "average utility",
C: "marginal utility.",
D: "time utility.",
answer: "C. marginal utility.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question12",
question:  "12. An increase in supply means that",
A: "more is sold at the same price.",
B: "more is sold at different prices.",
C: "there is a leftward shill of the supply curve.",
D: "there is a movement along the supply curve.",
answer: "D. there is a movement along the supply curve.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question13",
question:  "13. If an increase in the price of crude oil led to an increase in the price of kerosene and grease, then kerosene and grease are in",
A: "composite supply.",
B: "competitive supply.",
C: "market supply.",
D: "joint supply.",
answer: "D. joint supply.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question14",
question:  "14. A seller increased the quantity he offered for sale from 200 units to 250 units when price of his product increased by 12.5%. What is the price elasticity of supply of his product?",
A: "1.50",
B: "2.00",
C: "1.00",
D: "0.50",
answer: "B. 2.00",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question15",
question:  "15. If an increase in the supply of beef increased the supply of hides, then beef and hides are in",
A: "joint supply.",
B: "competitive supply.",
C: "composite supply.",
D: "joint demand.",
answer: "A. joint supply.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question16",
question:  "16. If a beef market is in equilibrium at $4.00 per kg, an increase in the price to $6.00 per kg may cause",
A: "rationing to be introduced",
B: "shortage in the market.",
C: "black market to come into operation.",
D: "surplus in the market.",
answer: "D. surplus in the market.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question17",
question:  "17. A large firm may experience diseconomies of scale of scale if there is",
A: "decrease in cost of production.",
B: "division of labour in production.",
C: "employment of more specialists.",
D: "difficulty in coordinating decisions.",
answer: "D. difficulty in coordinating decisions.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question18",
question:  "18. Increasing returns to scale suggests that",
A: "a firm can make profit by reducing output.",
B: "as the producer reduces the quantity of raw materials used, the marginal product will double.",
C: "a firm can make more profit by increasing output.",
D: "as the producer increases the quantity of raw materials used, the marginal product will fall.",
answer: "C. a firm can make more profit by increasing output.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question19",
question:  "19. One feature of the average fixed cost is that it",
A: "is U-shaped and intercepts the Y-axis.",
B: "falls continuously but is never equal to zero.",
C: "rises and falls faster than the marginal cost.",
D: "is always higher than the average variable cost.",
answer: "B. falls continuously but is never equal to zero.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question20",
question:  "20. If the average fixed cost (AFC) of producing 5 bags of rice is $ 20.00, the average fixed cost of producing  10 bags will be",
A: "$ 10.00",
B: "$ 4.00",
C: "$ 2.00",
D: "$ 20.00",
answer: "A. $ 10.00",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question21",
question:  "21. What is the unit price of the firm’s output?",
A: "$ 10.00",
B: "$ 2.00",
C: "$ 2.70",
D: "$ 1.70",
answer: "D. $ 1.70",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question22",
question:  "22. What is the firm’s marginal revenue?",
A: "$ 153.00",
B: "$ 0.80",
C: "$ 1.70",
D: "$ 17.00",
answer: "C. $ 1.70",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question23",
question:  "23. Organization and entrepreneurship are vested in different persons in",
A: "cooperative society.",
B: "sole proprietorship.",
C: "public company.",
D: "partnership.",
answer: "A. cooperative society.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question24",
question:  "24. The public sector in a mixed economy is not always efficient because of",
A: "the activities of shareholders.",
B: "the desire to make huge profit.",
C: "annual planning of activities.",
D: "bureaucratic practices.",
answer: "D. bureaucratic practices.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question25",
question:  "25. Which function of the wholesaler enables him to stabilize prices?",
A: "Advertising the goods",
B: "Warehousing goods",
C: "Granting credit to retailers",
D: "Transporting goods",
answer: "B. Warehousing goods",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question26",
question:  "26. In the long run, as individuals receive higher wages, it causes",
A: "supply of labour to decrease.",
B: "demand for leisure to decrease.",
C: "supply of normal goods to decrease.",
D: "demand for food to decrease.",
answer: "A. supply of labour to decrease.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question27",
question:  "27. Population growth rate can be calculated as",
A: "birth rate - death rate - emigrants - immigrants.",
B: "birth rate - death rate + immigrants - emigrants.",
C: "birth rate - death rate.",
D: "birth rate - death rate + migration rate - immigration rate.",
answer: "B. birth rate - death rate + immigrants - emigrants.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question28",
question:  "28. Labour productivity is defined as",
A: "the maximum number of hours worked.",
B: "average output.",
C: "output per man hour.",
D: "total output of labour.",
answer: "C. output per man hour.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question29",
question:  "29. Which of the following problems has the least effect on agricultural productivity in West Africa?",
A: "Urban-rural migration",
B: "Unfavorable weather conditions",
C: "Incidence of pests and diseases",
D: "Illiteracy",
answer: "D. Illiteracy",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question30",
question:  "30. The location of iron and steel industry at a place is due to",
A: "access to cheap labour.",
B: "easy access to raw materials.",
C: "government policy.",
D: "good infrastructure.",
answer: "B. easy access to raw materials.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question31",
question:  "31. Import substitution as a strategy of industrialization is the",
A: "replacement of locally produced goods with imported ones.",
B: "establishment of firms to process imported raw materials.",
C: "development of local firms to produce goods that are imported.",
D: "act of using local inputs to produce goods for export.",
answer: "C. development of local firms to produce goods that are imported.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question32",
question:  "32. Which of the following are intermediate products?",
A: "Table and door",
B: "Furniture and shirt",
C: "Handkerchief and shoe",
D: "Cement and steel",
answer: "D. Cement and steel",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question33",
question:  "33. Flow is NNP at factor cost derived from GNP at market prices?",
A: "GNP - Depreciation - Indirect taxes - Subsidies",
B: "GNP - Depreciation + Indirect taxes + Subsidies",
C: "GNP + Depreciation - Indirect taxes + Subsidies",
D: "GNP + Depreciation + Indirect taxes – Subsidies",
answer: "A. GNP - Depreciation - Indirect taxes – Subsidies",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question34",
question:  "34. Which of the following factors may lead to under-estimation of national income figures?",
A: "Availability of skilled statisticians",
B: "Subsistence production",
C: "Emigration of skilled workers to foreign countries",
D: "High volume of exports",
answer: "B. Subsistence production",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question35",
question:  "35. Inflation may occur if",
A: "rate of productivity is higher than wage rate.",
B: "prices fluctuate during a particular season of the year.",
C: "the government embarks on restrictive monetary policy.",
D: "wage increase is granted without increase in productivity.",
answer: "D. wage increase is granted without increase in productivity.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question36",
question:  "36. Money would cease to be a good store of value when",
A: "prices of goods and services are rising rapidly.",
B: "there is high level of unemployment.",
C: "prices of goods and services are falling slowly.",
D: "prices of goods and services are rising slowly.",
answer: "A. prices of goods and services are rising rapidly.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question37",
question:  "37. Governments in West Africa can curtail inflation by",
A: "encouraging banks to lend for consumption.",
B: "purchasing securities in the open market.",
C: "encouraging importation of goods from all countries.",
D: "selling securities in the open market.",
answer: "D. selling securities in the open market.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question38",
question:  "38. The central bank can reduce the ability of commercial banks to give out loans by",
A: "reducing the liquidity ratio.",
B: "reducing specific deposit.",
C: "raising the bank rate.",
D: "issuing more currency.",
answer: "C. raising the bank rate.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question39",
question:  "39. Tools of monetary policy do not include",
A: "open market operations.",
B: "tax and public expenditure.",
C: "bank rate.",
D: "reserve requirement.",
answer: "B. tax and public expenditure.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question40",
question:  "40. During inflation, the appropriate fiscal measure to adopt is to",
A: "increase indirect taxes.",
B: "reduce personal income tax.",
C: "increase direct taxes.",
D: "increase government expenditure.",
answer: "C. increase direct taxes.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question41",
question:  "41. Mr. X and Mrs. Y pay $ 500.00 and $ 1,400.00 as taxes on their earnings of $ 5,000.00 and $ 7,000.00 respectively. The system of taxation employed is",
A: "progressive tax.",
B: "proportional tax.",
C: "regressive tax.",
D: "specific tax.",
answer: "A. progressive tax.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question42",
question:  "42. expenditure n food takes a large proportion of incomes of people in",
A: "industrialized countries.",
B: "advanced counties.",
C: "capitalist counties.",
D: "developing countries.",
answer: "D. developing countries.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question43",
question:  "43. A country should embark on development planning to ensure that",
A: "it becomes popular among the comity of nations.",
B: "its scarce productive resources are efficiently utilized.",
C: "it also does what others are doing.",
D: "the nation is able to contribute its own quota to international organizations.",
answer: "B. its scarce productive resources are efficiently utilized.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question44",
question:  "44. A country is allowed to import just 50,000 tons of rice annually. This describes",
A: "quota.",
B: "tariff.",
C: "embargo.",
D: "devaluation.",
answer: "A. quota.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question45",
question:  "45. Dumping is selling goods in a foreign market at a price",
A: "equal to the cost of producing the goods.",
B: "above what is sold at the home market.",
C: "equal to what is sold at the home market.",
D: "below what is sold at the home market.",
answer: "D. below what is sold at the home market.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question46",
question:  "46. The principle of comparative advantage encourages a country to",
A: "Produce only consumer goods.",
B: "Try as much as possible to be self-sufficient.",
C: "Specialize in the production of all goods.",
D: "Engage in trade if it can produce a commodity at a lower cost.",
answer: "D. Engage in trade if it can produce a commodity at a lower cost.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question47",
question:  "47. in order to discourage the importation of manufactured goods a country should adopt",
A: "import substitution strategy.",
B: "export led strategy.",
C: "liberal foreign exchange.",
D: "import promotion strategy.",
answer: "A. import substitution strategy.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question48",
question:  "48. A free trade area is one in which",
A: "members adopt common external tariffs against non-members.",
B: "factor of production are mobile.",
C: "each member operates its own barriers against non-members.",
D: "members adopt common fiscal and economic policies.",
answer: "C. each member operates its own barriers against non-members.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question49",
question:  "49. The foremost objective of the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development (IBRD) is to",
A: "help promote private and public investments.",
B: "grant long term loans for infrastructure.",
C: "assist members achieve balance of payments stability.",
D: "maintain stability of foreign exchange.",
answer: "B. grant long term loans for infrastructure.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question50",
question:  "50. The exploitation of mineral resources constitutes which form of production?",
A: "service production.",
B: "secondary production.",
C: "tertiary production.",
D: "primary production.",
answer: "D. primary production.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},


]